<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: utilities | jtimberman's Code Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/categories/utilities/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-03T22:08:10-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joshua Timberman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Awesome Syntax Highlighting in Keynote]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2015/02/10/awesome-syntax-highlighting-in-keynote/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-10T21:31:49-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2015/02/10/awesome-syntax-highlighting-in-keynote</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am working on my presentation for ChefConf. I plan to have quite a lot of code samples. I&rsquo;ve found the options for getting code samples with nice syntax highlight a lackluster endeavour, with various GUI editors like TextMate, Sublime, and Atom having &ldquo;Copy as RTF&rdquo; plugins, but none of them being easily customizable.</p>

<p>So I did a quick Google search and happened on a gist I hadn&rsquo;t seen before. <a href="https://gist.github.com/jimbojsb/1630790">It</a> describes the following steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Install Homebrew (done, I have that covered with Chef ;)).</li>
<li>Install &ldquo;highlight&rdquo; with <code>brew install highlight</code>.</li>
<li>Use highlight to transform the source code file to RTF and copy it to the clipboard.</li>
<li>Paste the clipboard into Keynote.app.</li>
</ol>


<p>This isn&rsquo;t much different than the other solutions, except one super cool thing I learned about highlight.</p>

<p>It has styles.</p>

<p>```
highlight -w</p>

<p><OMG LIST OF EIGHTY TWO DIFFERENT STYLES!!!>
```</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s right, at least at the time of this writing highlight has 82 different styles available. Including my favorite(s) solarized &ndash; both light and dark. Note that the <code>--help</code> output says that this option is deprecated in the version I&rsquo;ve installed (3.18_1), but the styles are in <code>/usr/local/Cellar/highlight/VERSION/share/themes</code>.</p>

<p>Highlight knows the syntax highlighting for a lot of languages, these are in <code>/usr/local/Cellar/highlight/VERSION/share/langDefs</code>. For example I can get my Ruby recipe highlighted with this:</p>

<p><code>
highlight -s solarized-light -O rtf recipes/client.rb | pbcopy
</code></p>

<p>This will use Courier New as the font, and depending on the theme/style used, some of the highlighting may be bold or italic. This is easy enough to change in Keynote though.</p>

<p>For up to date documentation and information about highlight, visit the <a href="http://www.andre-simon.de/doku/highlight/en/highlight.php">author&rsquo;s page</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
