<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: windows | jtimberman's Code Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/categories/windows/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-17T22:59:19-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joshua Timberman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chef on Windows HTPC]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2011/11/21/chef-on-windows-htpc/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-21T07:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2011/11/21/chef-on-windows-htpc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past 20 years, I always had a Windows (or DOS!) PC as the
main system I use at home. The primary purpose was for gaming,
although building my own systems is also a hobby. In 2007, I wanted to
build a new system to use as a home theater PC. Originally, I built it
with Windows Vista &ndash; Windows Media Center <em>was</em> Vista&rsquo;s killer app! I
painstakingly installed software, tweaked system settings and tuned
the registry. Then Windows 7 came along with further
improvements. After almost 20 years of reinstalling from scratch for
new versions of Windows, I treated this upgrade as no
different.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I didn&rsquo;t capture all the system tweaks and settings. I
didn&rsquo;t get all the software reinstalled. I did what I remembered, and
W7 did have some improvements that made extra software and tweaks
unnecessary. The thing I was lacking in the rebuild, and up until
recently, was configuration management for Windows.</p>

<h2>Enter Chef</h2>

<p>Recently, my employer Opscode
<a href="http://www.opscode.com/press-releases/opscode-delivers-cloud-infrastructure-automation-to-windows-environments/">announced broader Windows support</a>
for Chef. The awesome Chef community, and our development team have
added some key features to Chef in the form of core libraries and
cookbooks. While I did get Chef running on my HTPC a few months ago, I
had only used it to test out the
<a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/powershell">powershell cookbook</a>,
and also wrote a
<a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/silverlight">silverlight cookbook</a>
as a proof of concept. In the mean time, the
<a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/windows">windows cookbook</a>
cookbook received some serious leveling up thanks to
<a href="http://twitter.com/schisamo">Seth Chisamore</a>.</p>

<h2>Windows Cookbook</h2>

<p>The Windows cookbook has a number of excellent &ldquo;primitives&rdquo; in the
form of libraries and resources. You can read all about that on
<a href="http://wiki.opscode.com/display/chef/Opscode+LWRP+Resources#OpscodeLWRPResources-windows">The Chef Wiki</a>. For
now, I&rsquo;ll talk about how I captured some of the configuration so I
don&rsquo;t have to remember next time (Windows 8, coming soon&hellip;). Of
interest here are the <code>windows_registry</code> and <code>windows_auto_run</code> resources.</p>

<h2>My HTPC&rsquo;s cookbooks</h2>

<p>I wrote two cookbooks this weekend. First, is a general &ldquo;Windows Media
Center&rdquo; cookbook called, aptly, &ldquo;<code>wmc</code>&rdquo;. This will capture the
specific registry and other configuration related to Windows Media
Center itself. The idea with this one is it manages only Windows Media
Center. It&rsquo;s not ready for release, but I&rsquo;ll post some snippets
of code here as I go.</p>

<p>The second cookbook I created is specifically for the Home Theater PC
itself, named <code>htpc</code>. This is going to contain all my preferences and
biases of how I want my HTPC to look like in order to provide
entertainment in my house.</p>

<h2>Windows Media Center (wmc)</h2>

<p>First and foremost, I want to make sure that Windows Media Center is
running at boot time, and the <code>windows_auto_run</code> resource fits the
bill. This resource modifies the registry to update the key
<code>HKLM\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Run</code>, using the
<code>windows_registry</code> resource. It does operate at the <em>machine</em> level,
not just the current user, but I only have one user on my HTPC, so
it&rsquo;s okay. Here&rsquo;s the resource:</p>

<p><code>ruby
windows_auto_run "Windows Media Center" do
  program "RunDLL32.exe C:/Windows/ehome/ehuihlp.exe,BootMediaCenter"
  not_if { Registry.value_exists?(AUTO_RUN_KEY, 'Windows Media Center') }
  action :create
end
</code></p>

<p>Next, I want to tweak a few other registry settings. Some of these I
discovered through an
<a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/astebner/archive/2006/04/29/586961.aspx">MSDN blog post</a>,
others are from setting up WMC itself and observing the &ldquo;HKCU&rdquo;
registry. Not the most sophisticated way, but I don&rsquo;t see a great
&ldquo;diff&rdquo; tool for the registry. Because the name of the HKCU and HKLM keys for WMC are
long, I set them to a couple local variables, via <code>cookbooks/attributes/default.rb</code>.</p>

<p><code>ruby
default['wmc']['reg_hkcu'] = 'HKCU\Software\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Media Center'
default['wmc']['reg_hklm'] = 'HKLM\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Media Center'
</code></p>

<p>Then in the recipe, I simply assign local variables.</p>

<p><code>ruby
hkcu = node['wmc']['reg_hkcu']
hklm = node['wmc']['reg_hklm']
</code></p>

<p>Now, for the registry changes. I use a 30 second skip forward and back
with my remote during recorded TV shows, so I can avoid commercials.</p>

<p>``` ruby
windows_registry &ldquo;#{hkcu}\Settings\VideoSettings&rdquo; do
  values(</p>

<pre><code>'SkipAheadInterval' =&gt; 0x7148,
'InstantReplayInterval' =&gt; 0x7148
</code></pre>

<p>  )
end
```</p>

<p>I also optimize the display for LCD/Plasma (I have a RP DLP, but I
digress).</p>

<p><code>ruby
windows_registry hkcu do
  values 'TVSkin' =&gt; 0
end
</code></p>

<p>For now, that&rsquo;s all the <code>wmc</code> cookbook has going for it. I do have
plans to enable additional features of WMC, install useful plugins,
and improve playback quality and performance. Mainly, I need to find
my old notes :&ndash;).</p>

<h2>Home Theater PC (htpc)</h2>

<p>The <code>htpc</code> cookbook will contain additional tweaks and settings for
how I want my HTPC configured. I don&rsquo;t know if I&rsquo;ll release it
publicly, as it is pretty specific to me, but it might be useful as
examples for others, so stay tuned to my
<a href="https://github.com/jtimberman">GitHub account</a> for updates.</p>

<p>First up are some local performance tweaks. These are done to
Explorer(.exe), and I don&rsquo;t remember the source.</p>

<p>``` ruby
windows_registry &ldquo;HKCU\Software\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Policies\Explorer&rdquo; do
  values(</p>

<pre><code>'NoLowDiskSpaceChecks' =&gt; 1,
'NoResolveSearch' =&gt; 1,
'NoResolveTrack' =&gt; 1
</code></pre>

<p>  )
end
```</p>

<p>Second, since this system is where all my music files live, I have
iTunes installed for
<a href="http://support.apple.com/kb/HT3819">Home Sharing</a>. It doesn&rsquo;t do much
good if iTunes isn&rsquo;t running, however, so I use <code>windows_auto_run</code> to
start it up.</p>

<p><code>ruby
windows_auto_run "iTunes" do
  program "C:/Program\ Files/iTunes/iTunes.exe"
  not_if { Registry.value_exists?(AUTO_RUN_KEY, "iTunes") }
  action :create
end
</code></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s pretty simple so far, but I have some plans in store for my HTPC cookbook.</p>

<h2>HTPC Cookbook Plans</h2>

<p>I do plan to add some new features to the <code>htpc</code> cookbook. First, I
want to make sure all the software I need is installed. While the
system mainly sits in WMC (with iTunes in the background), I do have
some additional software and utilities that I like to have for
managing my media library.</p>

<ul>
<li>iTunes &ndash; I already have the software installed, but it would be nice
to not have to do that during system setup (Windows 8, I say&hellip;).</li>
<li>Google Chrome &ndash; there&rsquo;s no abc.com, nbc.com, etc plugins for WMC
(yet?), so I need a browser to go to the respective web sites to
catch up on older episodes.</li>
<li>CDBurnerXP &ndash; decent CD/DVD burning software, rarely used but useful
for backups.</li>
<li>Logitech Harmony Remote Software &ndash; I have a
<a href="http://www.logitech.com/en-us/remotes/universal-remotes/devices/6063">Harmony 700 universal remote</a>
(and it&rsquo;s awesome!). This one might be tricky, but really I just
want to make sure the software is installed. Configuration profiles
are stored in an online support account with Logitech as far as I&rsquo;m
aware.</li>
<li>Netflix plugin for WMC &ndash; This will probably go into the <code>wmc</code>
cookbook, though.</li>
<li>Additional performance tweaks &ndash; There are a whole slew of tweaks
that I <em>know</em> I made, I just don&rsquo;t remember them all. These will be
added with <code>windows_registry</code> resources.</li>
<li>Manage services &ndash; Everyone who has a gaming PC knows about
<a href="http://www.blackviper.com/">Black Viper&rsquo;s Windows Service Guide(s)</a>.</li>
<li>Windows Features &ndash; With the <code>windows_feature</code> resource, Chef can
manage core features included in Windows installations.</li>
<li>Logging, monitoring &ndash; What kind of system administrator would I be
if I didn&rsquo;t also monitor my system for performance? :&ndash;)</li>
</ul>


<p>Some of the things I want to manage on my HTPC are covered by other
cookbooks I have, or exist on the
<a href="http://community.opscode.com">Chef Community Site</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Steam &ndash; This system is still capable of running some games, like
StarCraft II, TeamFortress 2 and Left 4 Dead (1 &amp; 2). I have a Steam
cookbook that works on OS X, it just isn&rsquo;t released (yet).</li>
<li>Teamspeak 3 &ndash; I already have a
<a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/teamspeak3">teamspeak3 cookbook</a>,
I&rsquo;ll just need to add installation of the client for Windows there.</li>
<li><a href="http://gnu.org/s/emacs">A text editor</a> &ndash; Since I have games, and
games have configuration files, it makes sense to &hellip; wait, I should
put those in Chef too! Or at least, in a Version Control System and
check out the repository&hellip;</li>
<li><a href="http://git-scm.org">Git</a> &ndash; For the above. This will likely be a
contribution to Opscode&rsquo;s
<a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/git">git cookbook</a>. Though
I&rsquo;ll still install a <a href="http://notepad-plus-plus.org">text editor</a> of
<a href="http://www.gnome.org/projects/gedit">some kind</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>These changes, updates and releases will be announced on this blog,
 mainly through my <a href="https://twitter.com/jtimberman">twitter</a> and
 <a href="https://plus.google.com/100567271038100401523/">Google+</a>
 accounts. Stay tuned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
