<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: chef, | jtimberman's Code Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/categories/chef/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-11T14:07:19-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joshua Timberman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chef 12: Fix Untrusted Self Sign Certs]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/12/11/chef-12-fix-untrusted-self-sign-certs/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T13:42:41-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/12/11/chef-12-fix-untrusted-self-sign-certs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Scenario: You&rsquo;ve started up a brand new Chef Server using version 12, and you have installed Chef 12 on your local system. You log into the Management Console to create a user and organization (or do this with the command-line <code>chef-server-ctl</code> commands), and you&rsquo;re ready to rock with this knife.rb:</p>

<p><code>ruby
node_name                'jtimberman'
client_key               'jtimberman.pem'
validation_client_name   'tester-validator'
validation_key           'tester-validator.pem'
chef_server_url          'https://chef-server.example.com/organizations/tester'
</code></p>

<p>However, when you try to check things out with knife:</p>

<p><code>
% knife client list
ERROR: SSL Validation failure connecting to host: ip-172-31-8-24.us-west-2.compute.internal - SSL_connect returned=1 errno=0 state=SSLv3 read server certificate B: certificate verify failed
ERROR: OpenSSL::SSL::SSLError: SSL_connect returned=1 errno=0 state=SSLv3 read server certificate B: certificate verify failed
</code></p>

<p>This is because Chef client 12 has SSL verification enabled by default for all requests. Since the certificate generated by the Chef Server 12 installation is self-signed, there isn&rsquo;t a signing CA that can be verified, and this fails. Never fear intrepid user, for you can get the SSL certificate from the server and store it as a &ldquo;trusted&rdquo; certificate. To find out how, use <code>knife ssl check</code>.</p>

<p>```
Connecting to host chef-server.example.com:443
ERROR: The SSL certificate of chef-server.example.com could not be verified
Certificate issuer data: /C=US/ST=WA/L=Seattle/O=YouCorp/OU=Operations/CN=chef-server.example.com/emailAddress=<a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#121;&#111;&#x75;&#64;&#x65;&#120;&#97;&#109;&#112;&#108;&#101;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#x6d;">&#121;&#111;&#117;&#64;&#x65;&#120;&#97;&#x6d;&#112;&#108;&#x65;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#109;</a></p>

<p>Configuration Info:</p>

<p>OpenSSL Configuration:
* Version: OpenSSL 1.0.1j 15 Oct 2014
* Certificate file: /opt/chefdk/embedded/ssl/cert.pem
* Certificate directory: /opt/chefdk/embedded/ssl/certs
Chef SSL Configuration:
* ssl_ca_path: nil
* ssl_ca_file: nil
* trusted_certs_dir: &ldquo;/Users/jtimberman/Downloads/chef-repo/.chef/trusted_certs&rdquo;</p>

<p>TO FIX THIS ERROR:</p>

<p>If the server you are connecting to uses a self-signed certificate, you must
configure chef to trust that server&rsquo;s certificate.</p>

<p>By default, the certificate is stored in the following location on the host
where your chef-server runs:</p>

<p>  /var/opt/chef-server/nginx/ca/SERVER_HOSTNAME.crt</p>

<p>Copy that file to your trusted_certs_dir (currently: /Users/jtimberman/Downloads/chef-repo/.chef/trusted_certs)
using SSH/SCP or some other secure method, then re-run this command to confirm
that the server&rsquo;s certificate is now trusted.
```</p>

<p>(note, <a href="https://github.com/opscode/chef/issues/2604">this chef-server location is incorrect</a>, it&rsquo;s <code>/var/opt/opscode</code>)</p>

<p>There is a <code>fetch</code> plugin for <code>knife</code> too. Let&rsquo;s download the certificate to the automatically preconfigured trusted certificate location mentioned in the output above.</p>

<p>```
% knife ssl fetch
WARNING: Certificates from ip-172-31-8-24.us-west-2.compute.internal will be fetched and placed in your trusted_cert
directory (/Users/jtimberman/Downloads/chef-repo/.chef/trusted_certs).</p>

<p>Knife has no means to verify these are the correct certificates. You should
verify the authenticity of these certificates after downloading.</p>

<p>Adding certificate for ip-172-31-8-24.us-west-2.compute.internal in /Users/jtimberman/Downloads/chef-repo/.chef/trusted_certs/ip-172-31-8-24_us-west-2_compute_internal.crt
```</p>

<p>The certificate should be verified that what was downloaded is in fact the same as the certificate on the Chef Server. For example, I compared SHA256 checksums:</p>

<p><code>
% ssh ubuntu@chef-server.example.com sudo sha256sum /var/opt/opscode/nginx/ca/chef-server.example.com.crt
043728b55144861ed43a426c67addca357a5889158886aee50685cf1422b5ebf  /var/opt/opscode/nginx/ca/chef-server.example.com.crt
% gsha256sum .chef/trusted_certs/chef-server.example.com.crt
043728b55144861ed43a426c67addca357a5889158886aee50685cf1422b5ebf  .chef/trusted_certs/chef-server.example.com.crt
</code></p>

<p>Now check knife client list again.</p>

<p><code>
% knife client list
tester-validator
</code></p>

<p>Victory!</p>

<p>Now, we need to get the ceritficate out to every node in the infrastructure in its <code>trusted_certs_dir</code> &ndash; by default this is <code>/etc/chef/trusted_certs</code>. The most simple way to do this is to use <code>knife ssh</code> to run knife on the target nodes.</p>

<p><code>
% knife ssh 'name:*' 'sudo knife ssl fetch -c /etc/chef/client.rb'
node-output.example.com WARNING: Certificates from chef-server-example.com will be fetched and placed in your trusted_cert
node-output.example.com directory (/etc/chef/trusted_certs).
node-output.example.com
node-output.example.com Knife has no means to verify these are the correct certificates. You should
node-output.example.com verify the authenticity of these certificates after downloading.
node-output.example.com
node-output.example.com Adding certificate for chef-server.example.com in /etc/chef/trusted_certs/chef-server.example.com.crt
</code></p>

<p>The output will be interleaved for all the nodes returned by <code>knife ssh</code>. Of course, we should verify the SHA256 checksums like before, which can be done again with <code>knife ssh</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflecting on Six Years with Chef]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/10/07/reflecting-on-six-years-with-chef/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-07T11:36:43-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/10/07/reflecting-on-six-years-with-chef</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It actually started a bit over seven years ago. I saw the writing on the wall at IBM; my job was soon to be outsourced. I found an open position with the SANS institute, accepted an offer there, and was due to start work in a couple of weeks. Around the same time, my friends Adam Jacob and Nathan Haneysmith had started HJK Solutions. They invited me to join them then, but it wasn&rsquo;t the right time for me. Adam told me that at SANS I should at least use the <a href="https://puppetlabs.com">automation</a> <a href="http://capistranorb.com/">tools</a> and general <a href="http://infrastructures.org">infrastructure management model</a> they planned to use. It turned out this was sage advice, for a number of reasons.</p>

<p>Around April, 2008, Adam told me he was working on &ldquo;Chef,&rdquo; a Ruby based configuration management and system integration framework. I was excited about its potential, and a few months later on July 2, 2008, I started with HJK Solutions as a Linux system administration consultant. I got familiar with HJK&rsquo;s puppet-based stack, and ancillary Ruby tools like <a href="https://github.com/adamhjk/iclassify/wiki">iClassify</a> while working on their customer infrastructures over the coming months. After Opscode was founded and we released Chef 0.5, my primary focus was porting HJK&rsquo;s puppet modules to <a href="https://github.com/opscode/cookbooks">chef cookbooks</a>.</p>

<h2>opscode/cookbooks</h2>

<p>Adam had started the repository to give new users a place to begin using Chef with full working examples. I continued their development, and had the opportunity to solve hard problems of integration web application stacks with them. There were three important reasons for the repository to exist:</p>

<ol>
<li>We have a body of knowledge as a tribe, and that can be codified.</li>
<li>Infrastructure as code is real, and it <em>can</em> be reusable.</li>
<li>The best way to learn Chef is to use Chef, and I had a goal to know Chef well enough to teach it to new users and companies.</li>
</ol>


<p>The development of general purpose cookbooks ends up being harder than any of us really imagined, I think. Every platform is different, so not only did I have to learn Chef, I had to learn how different platforms behave for common (and uncommon) pieces of software in web operations stacks. Over the years of managing these cookbooks, I learned a lot about how the community was developing workflows for using Chef, and how they differed from our opinions. I learned also learned how to manage and contribute to open source projects at a rather large scale, and how to have compassion and empathy for new or frustrated users.</p>

<h2>Training and Services</h2>

<p>In my time at CHEF, nee Opscode, I&rsquo;ve had several job role changes. After several months of working on cookbooks, I added package and release management (<a href="http://lists.opscode.com/sympa/arc/chef/2014-11/msg00015.html">RIP, apt.opscode.com</a>) to my repertoire. I then switched to technical evangelism and training. With mentorship from <a href="http://twitter.com/botchagalupe">John Willis</a>, I drafted the initial version of <a href="https://www.getchef.com/blog/2010/07/13/open-source-chef-training-open-training/">Chef Fundamentals</a>, and delivered our inaugural training class in Seattle.</p>

<p>I worked with the team John built to deliver training, speak at conferences, and work directly with customers to help make them successful with Chef. Eventually, John left the company to <a href="http://www.enstratius.com/news-events/press-releases/john-willis-announcement">build an awesome team</a> at <a href="http://www.enstratius.com/home">Enstratius</a>. I took on the role of Director of the team, but eventually I discovered that the <a href="http://fractio.nl/2014/09/19/not-a-promotion-a-career-change/">management track</a> was not the future of my career.</p>

<h2>Open Source and Community</h2>

<p>I came back to working on the cookbooks, which I had previously <a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks">split into separate repositories</a>. I was also working more directly in the community, doing public training classes only (our consulting team did private/onsite classes), participating in our <a href="https://botbot.me/freenode/chef">IRC channels</a> and mailing <a href="http://lists.opscode.com">lists</a>. We had some organization churn, and I was moved around between four different managers, eventually reporting to <a href="https://twitter.com/nathenharvey">the inimitable Nathen Harvey</a>.</p>

<p>During one of our 1-1 discussions, he said, &ldquo;You know, Joshua. You write a lot of cookbooks to automate infrastructure. But you haven&rsquo;t actually worked on any infrastructure in years. You should do something about that.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Around that time, there was a &ldquo;senior system administrator&rdquo; job posting on our very own careers site. I talked to our VP of Operations, and after a brief transition period, moved completely over to the ops team. I was able to bring with me the great practices from the community for developing cookbooks: testing with <a href="http://sethvargo.github.io/chefspec/">chefspec</a> and <a href="http://serverspec.org/">serverspec</a>, code consistency with <a href="">rubocop</a> and <a href="http://foodcritic.io">foodcritic</a>, and wrapping it all up with <a href="http://kitchen.ci">test kitchen</a>.</p>

<h2>The Future</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had the privilege to do work that I love, which is automating hard problems using Chef. I&rsquo;ve also had the privilege of being part of the web operations, infrastructure as code, devops, and Chef communities over the past six years. I&rsquo;ve been to all four Chef summits, and all three ChefConfs. A thing I&rsquo;ve noticed over the years is that many conversations keep coming up at the summits and ChefConf. Fresh on my mind because the last summit was so recent is the topic of cookbook reusability. See, during the time that I managed opscode/cookbooks, I eventually saw the point people in the community were making about these being real software repositories that need to be managed like other complex software projects. We split up the repository into individual repositories per cookbook. We started adding test coverage, and conforming to consistency via syntax and style lint checking. That didn&rsquo;t make cookboks more reusable, but it lowered the barrier of contribution, which in turn made them more reusable as more use cases could be covered. I got to be a part of that evolution, and it&rsquo;s been awesome.</p>

<p>While using Chef is one of my favorite technical things to do, I have come to the conclusion that based on my experience the best thing I can do is be a facilitator of stronger technical discipline with regard to using Chef. Primarily, this means improving how CHEF uses Chef to build Chef for our community and customers. We&rsquo;re already really good at using Chef to build Chef (the product), and run Hosted Chef (the service). However, awesome tools from the community such as Test Kitchen, Berkshelf, ChefSpec, and Foodcritic did not exist when we started out. Between new, awesome tools, and growing our organization with new awesome people, we need to improve on getting our team members up to speed on the process and workflow that helps us deliver higher quality products.</p>

<p>That is why I&rsquo;m moving into a new role at CHEF. The sixth year marks as good a time as any to make a change, and I&rsquo;m no stranger to that. I&rsquo;m joining a team of quality advocacy led by Joseph Smith, as part of Jez Humble&rsquo;s &ldquo;Office of Continuous Improvement and Velocity.&rdquo; In this new role, I will focus on improving our overall technical excellence so we can deliver better products to our community and customers, and so we can have awesome use cases and examples for managing Chef Server and its add-ons at scale.</p>

<p>My first short term goal in this new role is a workstation automation cookbook that can be used and extended by our internal teams for ensuring everyone has a consistent set of tools to work on the product. This will be made an open source project that the community can use and extend as well. We&rsquo;ll have more information about this as it becomes &ldquo;a thing.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Next, I want to improve how we work on incidents. We&rsquo;ve had sporadic blog posts about issues in Hosted Chef and Supermarket, and I&rsquo;d like to see this get better.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also interested in managing Chef Server 12 clusters, including all the add-ons. Recently I worked on the <a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/chef-server-cluster">chef-server-cluster</a> cookbook, which will become the way CHEF deploys and manages Hosted Chef using the version 12 packages. Part of the earliest days of opscode/cookbooks, I maintained cookbooks to setup the open source Chef Server. Long time users may remember the &ldquo;chef solo bootstrap&rdquo; stack. Since then, CHEF has continued to iterate on that idea, and the &ldquo;ctl&rdquo; management commands largely use chef-solo under the hood. The new cookbook combines and wraps up manual processes and the &ldquo;ctl&rdquo; commands to enable us, our community, and our customers to build scalable Chef Server clusters using the omnibus packages. The cookbook uses chef-provisioning to do much of the heavy lifting.</p>

<p>It should be easy for organizations to be successful with Chef. That includes CHEF! My goal in my new position is to fuel the love of Chef internally and externally, whip up awesome, and stir up more delight. I also look forward to seeing what our community and customers do with Chef in their organizations.</p>

<h2>Thank you</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to thank the friends and mentors I&rsquo;ve had along this journey. You&rsquo;re all important, and we&rsquo;ve shared some good times and code, and sometimes hugs. It&rsquo;s been amazing to see so many people become successful with Chef.</p>

<p>Above all, I&rsquo;d like to thank Adam Jacob: for the opportunity to join in this ride, for inspiration to be a better system administrator and operations professional, for mentorship along the way, and for writing Chef in the first place. Cheers, my friend.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s to many more years of whipping up awesome!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chef Reporting API and Resource Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/10/07/chef-reporting-api-and-resource-updates/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-07T06:18:34-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/10/07/chef-reporting-api-and-resource-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever wanted to find a list of nodes that updated a specific resource in a period of time? Such as &ldquo;show me all the nodes in production that had an application service restart in the last hour&rdquo;? Or, &ldquo;which nodes have updated their apt cache recently?&rdquo; For example,</p>

<p><code>
% knife report resource 'role:supermarket-app AND chef_environment:supermarket-prod' execute 'apt-get update'
execute[apt-get update] changed in the following runs:
app-supermarket1.example.com 2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802 @ 2014-10-07T14:07:03Z
app-supermarket2.example.com c5e4d7bf-95a6-4385-9d8e-c6f5617ed79b @ 2014-10-07T14:14:04Z
app-supermarket3.example.com c4c4b4bb-91b6-4f73-9876-b24b093c7f1e @ 2014-10-07T14:09:54Z
app-supermarket4.example.com 3eb09034-7539-4a3c-af6d-5b01d35bc63f @ 2014-10-07T13:31:56Z
app-supermarket5.example.com aa48c1d3-da91-4031-a43d-582a577cbf2d @ 2014-10-07T13:35:15Z
Use `knife runs show` with the run UUID to get more info
</code></p>

<p>I have released a new knife plugin to do that, but first some background.</p>

<p>At CHEF, we run the community&rsquo;s cookbook site, <a href="https://supermarket.getchef.com">Supermarket</a>. We monitor the systems that run the site with <a href="http://sensuapp.org">Sensu</a>. The current infrastructure runs instances on Amazon Web Services EC2, with an Elastic Load Balancer (ELB) in front of them. As a corrective action for a <a href="https://www.getchef.com/blog/2014/07/10/supermarket-intermittent-unresponsiveness-postmortem/">Supermarket outage</a>, CHEF&rsquo;s operations team added a new check for elevated HTTP 500 responses from the application servers behind the ELB. One thing we found was that when Supermarket was deployed, and the <code>unicorn</code> server restarted, we would see elevated 500&rsquo;s, but the site often wouldn&rsquo;t actually be impacted.</p>

<p>The Sensu check is run from a &ldquo;relay&rdquo; node. That is, it isn&rsquo;t run on the application servers or the Sensu server &ndash; it&rsquo;s run out of band since it&rsquo;s for the ELB. One might imagine we could have similar checks for other services that aren&rsquo;t run on &ldquo;managed nodes,&rdquo; but that&rsquo;s neither here nor there. The issue is that we get an alert message that looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
Sensu Alerts     ALERT - [i-d1dfd5d9/check-elb-backend-500] - CheckELBMetrics CRITICAL: supermarket-elb; Sum of HTTPCode_Backend_5XX is 2538.0. (expected lower than 30.0); (HTTPCode_Backend_5XX '2538.0' within 300 seconds between 2014-08-19 13:33:36 +0000 to 2014-08-19 13:38:36 +0000) [Playbook].
</code></p>

<p>The first part, <code>[i-d1dfd5d9/check-elb-backend-500]</code> is the node name and the check that alerted. The node name here is the monitoring relay that runs the check, not the actual node or nodes where Supermarket was deployed and restarted. This is where Chef Reporting comes into play. In Chef Reporting, we can view information about recent Chef client runs, which gives us a graph like this.</p>

<p><img src="/images/reporting-graph.png"></p>

<p>If we go look at the reports in the Chef Manage console, we can drill down to something like this.</p>

<p><img src="/images/reporting-resources.png"></p>

<p>This shows that unicorn was restarted in this run. That&rsquo;s great, but if I&rsquo;m getting this alert at a time when I&rsquo;m not particularly coherent (e.g, 2AM), I want a command in a playbook that I can run to get more information quickly without having to log into the webui and click around imprecisely. CHEF publishes a <code>knife-reporting</code> gem that has a couple handy sub-commands to retrieve this run data. For example, we can list runs.</p>

<p>```
% knife runs list
node_name:  i-3022aa3b
run_id:     9eccd8f6-876b-4a57-87ac-0b3e7b7ef1e7
start_time: 2014-08-21T17:03:56Z
status:     started</p>

<p>node_name:  i-a09424a8
run_id:     f2b7871a-149b-4fd3-abdc-d74a838d719a
start_time: 2014-08-21T17:00:23Z
status:     success
```</p>

<p>Or, we can display a specific run.</p>

<p>```
% knife runs show eecb04fb-11df-438a-8e81-dd610eb66616
run_detail:
  data:
  end_time:          2014-08-20T17:50:12Z
  node_name:         i-9f22aa94
  run_id:            eecb04fb-11df-438a-8e81-dd610eb66616
  run_list:          [&ldquo;role[base]&rdquo;,&ldquo;role[supermarket-app]&rdquo;]
  start_time:        2014-08-20T17:45:37Z
  status:            success
  total_res_count:   261
  updated_res_count: 17
run_resources:
  cookbook_name:    supermarket
  cookbook_version: 2.7.2
  duration:         209
  final_state:</p>

<pre><code>enabled: false
running: true
</code></pre>

<p>  id:               unicorn
  initial_state:</p>

<pre><code>enabled: false
running: true
</code></pre>

<p>  name:             unicorn
  result:           restart
  type:             service
  uri:              <a href="https://api.opscode.com/organizations/supermarket/reports/org/runs/eecb04fb-11df-438a-8e81-dd610eb66616/15">https://api.opscode.com/organizations/supermarket/reports/org/runs/eecb04fb-11df-438a-8e81-dd610eb66616/15</a>
```</p>

<p>This is handy, but a little limited. What if I want to display only the runs containing the <code>service[unicorn]</code> resource?</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s where my <code>knife-report-resource</code> plugin helps. At first, it was very much specific to finding unicorn restarts on Supermarket app servers. However, I wanted to make it more general purpose as I think people would want to be able to find when arbitrary resources were updated. This is how it works:</p>

<ol>
<li>Query the Chef Server for a particular set of nodes. For example, <code>'role:supermarket-app AND chef_environment:supermarket-prod'</code>.</li>
<li>Get all the Chef client runs for a specified time period up until the current time. By default, it starts from one hour ago, but we can pass an ISO8601 timestamp.</li>
<li>Iterate over all the runs looking for runs by the nodes that were returned by the search query, gathering the specified resource type and name.</li>
<li>Display some nice output with the node&rsquo;s FQDN, the run&rsquo;s UUID, and a timestamp.</li>
</ol>


<p>From the earlier example:</p>

<p><code>
% knife report resource 'role:supermarket-app AND chef_environment:supermarket-prod' execute 'apt-get update'
execute[apt-get update] changed in the following runs:
app-supermarket1.example.com 2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802 @ 2014-10-07T14:07:03Z
app-supermarket2.example.com c5e4d7bf-95a6-4385-9d8e-c6f5617ed79b @ 2014-10-07T14:14:04Z
app-supermarket3.example.com c4c4b4bb-91b6-4f73-9876-b24b093c7f1e @ 2014-10-07T14:09:54Z
app-supermarket4.example.com 3eb09034-7539-4a3c-af6d-5b01d35bc63f @ 2014-10-07T13:31:56Z
app-supermarket5.example.com aa48c1d3-da91-4031-a43d-582a577cbf2d @ 2014-10-07T13:35:15Z
Use `knife runs show` with the run UUID to get more info
</code></p>

<p>Then, we can drill down further into one of these runs with the <code>knife-reporting</code> plugin.</p>

<p>```
% knife runs show 2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802
run_detail:
  data:
  end_time:          2014-10-07T14:07:03Z
  node_name:         i-d7fed0df
  run_id:            2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802
  run_list:          [&ldquo;role[base]&rdquo;,&ldquo;role[supermarket-app]&rdquo;]
  start_time:        2014-10-07T14:03:59Z
  status:            success
  total_res_count:   271
  updated_res_count: 12
run_resources:
  cookbook_name:    chef-client
  cookbook_version: 3.6.0
  duration:         99
  final_state:</p>

<pre><code>enabled: true
running: false
</code></pre>

<p>  id:               chef-client
  initial_state:</p>

<pre><code>enabled: true
running: true
</code></pre>

<p>  name:             chef-client
  result:           enable
  type:             runit_service
  uri:              <a href="https://api.opscode.com/organizations/supermarket/reports/org/runs/2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802/0">https://api.opscode.com/organizations/supermarket/reports/org/runs/2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802/0</a>
&hellip;
  cookbook_name:    supermarket
  cookbook_version: 2.11.0
  duration:         8506
  final_state:
  id:               apt-get update
  initial_state:
  name:             apt-get update
  result:           run
  type:             execute
  uri:              <a href="https://api.opscode.com/organizations/supermarket/reports/org/runs/2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802/5">https://api.opscode.com/organizations/supermarket/reports/org/runs/2230cf30-6d95-4e43-be18-211137eaf802/5</a>
```</p>

<p>Hopefully you find this plugin useful! It is a RubyGem, and is available on RubyGems.org, and the source is available on GitHub.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://supermarket.getchef.com/tools/knife-report-resource">Supermarket tool page</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/knife-report-resource">RubyGem page</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jtimberman/knife-report-resource">GitHub repository</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evolution of Cookbook Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/02/01/evolution-of-cookbook-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-01T12:48:49-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2014/02/01/evolution-of-cookbook-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I will explore some development patterns that I&rsquo;ve seen
(and done!) with Chef cookbooks, and then explain how we can evolve to
a new level of cookbook development. The examples here come from
Chef&rsquo;s new
<a href="http://www.getchef.com/blog/2014/01/28/chefs-splunk-cookbook-2/">chef-splunk cookbook</a>,
which is a refactored version of an old <code>splunk42</code> cookbook. While
there is a public <code>splunk</code> cookbook on the Chef community site, it
shares some of the issues that I saw with our old one, which are
partially subject matter of this post.</p>

<p>Anyway, on to the evolution!</p>

<h1>Sub-optimal patterns</h1>

<p>These are the general patterns I&rsquo;m going to address.</p>

<ul>
<li>Composing URLs from multiple local variables or attributes</li>
<li>Large conditional logic branches like case statements in recipes</li>
<li>Not using definitions when it is best to do so</li>
<li>Knowledge of how node run lists are composed for search, or
searching for &ldquo;<code>role:some-server</code>&rdquo;</li>
<li>Repeated resources across multiple orthogonal recipes</li>
<li>Plaintext secrets in attributes or data bag items</li>
</ul>


<p>Cookbook development is a wide and varied topic, so there are many
other patterns to consider, but these are the ones most relevant to
the refactored cookbook.</p>

<h2>Composing URLs</h2>

<p>It may seem like a good idea, to compose URL strings as attributes or
local variables in a recipe based on other attributes and local
variables. For example, in our <code>splunk42</code> cookbook we have this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
splunk_root = "http://download.splunk.com/releases/"
splunk_version = "4.2.1"
splunk_build = "98164"
splunk_file = "splunkforwarder-#{splunk_version}-#{splunk_build}-linux-2.6-amd64.deb"
os = node['os'].gsub(/\d*/, '')
</code></p>

<p>These get used in the following <code>remote_file</code> resource:</p>

<p><code>ruby
remote_file "/opt/#{splunk_file}" do
  source "#{splunk_root}/#{splunk_version}/universalforwarder/#{os}/#{splunk_file}"
  action :create_if_missing
end
</code></p>

<p>We reused the filename variable, and composed the URL to the file to
download. Then to upgrade, we can simply modify the <code>splunk_version</code>
and <code>splunk_build</code>, as Splunk uses a consistent naming theme for their
package URLs (thanks, Splunk!). The filename itself is built from a
case statement (more on that in the next section). We could further
make the version and build attributes, so users can update to newer
versions by simply changing the attribute.</p>

<p>So what is bad about this? Two things.</p>

<ol>
<li>This is in the <code>splunk42::client</code> recipe, and repeated again in the
<code>splunk42::server</code> recipe with only minor differences (the package
name, splunk vs splunkforwarder).</li>
<li>Ruby has excellent libraries for manipulating URIs and paths as
strings, and it is easier to break up a string than compose a new one.</li>
</ol>


<p>How can this be improved? First, we can set attributes for the full URL.
The actual code for that is below, but suffice to say, it will look
like this (note the version is different because the new cookbook installs
a new Splunk version).</p>

<p><code>ruby
default['splunk']['forwarder']['url'] = 'http://download.splunk.com/releases/6.0.1/universalforwarder/linux/splunkforwarder-6.0.1-189883-linux-2.6-amd64.deb'
</code></p>

<p>Second, we have
<a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/chef-splunk/blob/master/libraries/helpers.rb">helper libraries</a>
distributed with the cookbook that break up the URI so we can return
just the package filename.</p>

<p><code>ruby
def splunk_file(uri)
  require 'pathname'
  require 'uri'
  Pathname.new(URI.parse(uri).path).basename.to_s
end
</code></p>

<p>The previous <code>remote_file</code> resource is rewritten like this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
remote_file "/opt/#{splunk_file(node['splunk']['forwarder']['url'])}" do
  source node['splunk']['forwarder']['url']
  action :create_if_missing
end
</code></p>

<p>As a bonus, the helper methods are available in other places like
other cookbooks and recipes, rather than the local scope of local
variables.</p>

<h2>Conditional Logic Branches</h2>

<p>One of the wonderful things about Chef is that simple Ruby
conditionals can be used in recipes to selectively set values for
resource attributes, define resources that should be used, and other
decisions. One of the horrible things about Chef is that simple Ruby
conditionals can be used in recipes and often end up being far more
complicated than originally intended, especially when handling
multiple platforms and versions.</p>

<p>In the earlier example, we had a <code>splunk_file</code> local variable set in a
recipe. I mentioned it was built from a case statement, which looks
like this, in full:</p>

<p>```ruby
splunk_file = case node[&lsquo;platform_family&rsquo;]
  when &ldquo;rhel&rdquo;</p>

<pre><code>if node['kernel']['machine'] == "x86_64"
  splunk_file = "splunkforwarder-#{splunk_version}-#{splunk_build}-linux-2.6-x86_64.rpm"
else
  splunk_file = "splunkforwarder-#{splunk_version}-#{splunk_build}.i386.rpm"
end
</code></pre>

<p>  when &ldquo;debian&rdquo;</p>

<pre><code>if node['kernel']['machine'] == "x86_64"
  splunk_file = "splunkforwarder-#{splunk_version}-#{splunk_build}-linux-2.6-amd64.deb"
else
  splunk_file = "splunkforwarder-#{splunk_version}-#{splunk_build}-linux-2.6-intel.deb"
end
</code></pre>

<p>  when &ldquo;omnios&rdquo;</p>

<pre><code>splunk_file = "splunkforwarder-#{splunk_version}-#{splunk_build}-solaris-10-intel.pkg.Z"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
```</p>

<p>Splunk itself supports many platforms, and not all of them are covered
by this conditional, so it&rsquo;s easy to imagine how this can get further
out of control and make the recipe even harder to follow. Also
consider that this is just the <code>client</code> portion for the
<code>splunkforwarder</code> package, this same block is repeated in the <code>server</code>
recipe, for the <code>splunk</code> package.</p>

<p>So why is this bad? There are three reasons.</p>

<ol>
<li>We have a large block of conditionals that sit in front of a user
reading a recipe.</li>
<li>This logic isn&rsquo;t reusable elsewhere, so it has to be duplicated in
the other recipe.</li>
<li>This is only the logic for the package filename, but we care about
the entire URL. I&rsquo;ve also covered that composing URLs isn&rsquo;t delightful.</li>
</ol>


<p>What is a better approach? Use the full URL as I mentioned before, and
set it as an attribute. We will still have the gnarly case statement,
but it will be tucked away in the <code>attributes/default.rb</code> file, and
hidden from anyone reading the recipe (which is the thing they
probably care most about reading).</p>

<p>```ruby
case node[&lsquo;platform_family&rsquo;]
when &lsquo;rhel&rsquo;
  if node[&lsquo;kernel&rsquo;][&lsquo;machine&rsquo;] == &lsquo;x86_64&rsquo;</p>

<pre><code>default['splunk']['forwarder']['url'] = 'http://download.splunk.com/releases/6.0.1/universalforwarder/linux/splunkforwarder-6.0.1-189883-linux-2.6-x86_64.rpm'
default['splunk']['server']['url'] = 'http://download.splunk.com/releases/6.0.1/splunk/linux/splunk-6.0.1-189883-linux-2.6-x86_64.rpm'
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>default['splunk']['forwarder']['url'] = 'http://download.splunk.com/releases/6.0.1/universalforwarder/linux/splunkforwarder-6.0.1-189883.i386.rpm'
default['splunk']['server']['url'] = 'http://download.splunk.com/releases/6.0.1/splunk/linux/splunk-6.0.1-189883.i386.rpm'
</code></pre>

<p>  end
when &lsquo;debian&rsquo;
  # &hellip;
```</p>

<p>The the complete case block can be viewed in the
<a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/chef-splunk/blob/master/attributes/default.rb#L46-L66">repository</a>.
Also, since this is an attribute, consumers of this cookbook can set
the URL to whatever they want, including a local HTTP server.</p>

<p>Another example of gnarly conditional logic looks like this, also from
the <code>splunk42::client</code> recipe.</p>

<p>```ruby
case node[&lsquo;platform_family&rsquo;]
when &ldquo;rhel&rdquo;
  rpm_package &ldquo;/opt/#{splunk_file}&rdquo; do</p>

<pre><code>source "/opt/#{splunk_file}"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
when &ldquo;debian&rdquo;
  dpkg_package &ldquo;/opt/#{splunk_file}&rdquo; do</p>

<pre><code>source "/opt/#{splunk_file}"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
when &ldquo;omnios&rdquo;
  # tl;dr, this was more lines than you want to read, and
  # will be covered in the next section.
end
```</p>

<p>Why is this bad? After all, we&rsquo;re selecting the proper package
resource to install from a local file on disk. The main issue is the
conditional creates different resources that can&rsquo;t be looked up in the
resource collection. Our recipe doesn&rsquo;t do this, but perhaps a wrapper
cookbook would. The consumer wrapping the cookbook has to duplicate
this logic in their own. Instead, it is better to select the provider
for a single <code>package</code> resource.</p>

<p>```ruby
package &ldquo;/opt/#{splunk_file(node[&lsquo;splunk&rsquo;][&lsquo;forwarder&rsquo;][&lsquo;url&rsquo;])}&rdquo; do
  case node[&lsquo;platform_family&rsquo;]
  when &lsquo;rhel&rsquo;</p>

<pre><code>provider Chef::Provider::Package::Rpm
</code></pre>

<p>  when &lsquo;debian&rsquo;</p>

<pre><code>provider Chef::Provider::Package::Dpkg
</code></pre>

<p>  when &lsquo;omnios&rsquo;</p>

<pre><code>provider Chef::Provider::Package::Solaris
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<h2>Definitions Aren&rsquo;t Bad</h2>

<p>Definitions are simply defined as recipe &ldquo;macros.&rdquo; They are not
actually Chef Resources themselves, they just look like them, and
contain their own Chef resources. This has some disadvantages, such as
lack of metaparameters (like action), which has lead people to prefer
using the &ldquo;Lightweight Resource/Provider&rdquo; (LWRP) DSL instead. In fact,
some feel that definitions are bad, and that one should feel bad for
using them. I argue that they have their place. One advantage is their
relative simplicity.</p>

<p>In our <code>splunk42</code> cookbook, the client and server recipes duplicate a
lot of logic. As mentioned a lot of this is case statements for the
Splunk package file. They also repeat the same logic for choosing the
provider to install the package. I snipped the content from the <code>when
"omnios"</code> block, but it looks like this:</p>

<p>`&ldquo;ruby
cache_dir = Chef::Config[:file_cache_path]
splunk_pkg = splunk_file.gsub(/.Z/, &rdquo;)</p>

<p>execute &ldquo;uncompress /opt/#{splunk_file}&rdquo; do
  not_if { ::File.exists?(splunk_cmd) }
end</p>

<p>cookbook_file &ldquo;#{cache_dir}/splunk-nocheck&rdquo; do
  source &ldquo;splunk-nocheck&rdquo;
end</p>

<p>file &ldquo;#{cache_dir}/splunkforwarder-response&rdquo; do
  content &ldquo;BASEDIR=/opt&rdquo;
end</p>

<p>pkgopts = [&ldquo;-a #{cache_dir}/splunk-nocheck&rdquo;,</p>

<pre><code>       "-r #{cache_dir}/splunkforwarder-response"]
</code></pre>

<p>package &ldquo;splunkforwarder&rdquo; do
  source &ldquo;/opt/#{splunk_pkg}&rdquo;
  options pkgopts.join(&lsquo; &rsquo;)
  provider Chef::Provider::Package::Solaris
end
```</p>

<p>(Note: the logic for setting the provider is required since we&rsquo;re not using the default over-the-network package providers, and installing from a local file on the system.)</p>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t <em>too</em> bad on its own, but needs to be repeated again in the
server recipe if one wanted to run a Splunk server on OmniOS. The
actual differences between the client and server package installation
are the package name, <code>splunkforwarder</code> vs <code>splunk</code>. The earlier URL
attribute example established a <code>forwarder</code> and <code>server</code> attribute.
Using a definition, named <code>splunk_installer</code>, allows us to simplify
the package installation used by the client and server recipes to look
like this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
splunk_installer 'splunkforwarder' do
  url node['splunk']['forwarder']['url']
end
splunk_installer 'splunk' do
  url node['splunk']['server']['url']
end
</code></p>

<p>How is this better than an LWRP? Simply that there was less ceremony
in creating it. There is less cognitive load for a cookbook developer
to worry about. Definitions by their very nature of containing
resources are already idempotent and convergent with no additional
effort. They also automatically support why-run mode, whereas in an
LWRP that must be done by the developer. Finally, between resources in
the definition and the rest of the Chef run, notifications may be
sent.</p>

<p>Contrast this to an LWRP, we need <code>resources</code> and <code>providers</code>
directories, and the attributes of the resource need to be defined in
the resource. Then the action methods need to be written in the
provider. If we&rsquo;re using inline resources (which we are) we need to
declare those so any notifications work. Finally, we should ensure
that why-run works properly.</p>

<p>The actual definition is ~40 lines, and can be viewed in the cookbook
<a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/chef-splunk/blob/master/definitions/splunk_installer.rb">repository</a>.
I don&rsquo;t have a comparable LWRP for this, but suffice to say that it
would be longer and more complicated than the definition.</p>

<h2>Reasonability About Search</h2>

<p>Search is one of the killer features of running a Chef Server.
Dynamically configuring load balancer configuration, or finding the
master database server is simple with a search. Because we often think
about the functionality a service provides based on the role it
serves, we end up doing searches that look like this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
splunk_servers = search(:node, "role:splunk-server")
</code></p>

<p>Then we do something with <code>splunk_servers</code>, like send it to a
template. What if someone doesn&rsquo;t like the <a href="http://bikeshed.io">role name</a>?
Then we have to do something like this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
splunk_servers = search(:node, "role:#{node['splunk']['server_role']}")
</code></p>

<p>Then consumers of the cookbook can use whatever server role name they
want, and just update the attribute for it. But, the internet has said
that roles are bad, so we shouldn&rsquo;t use them (even though they
aren&rsquo;t ;)). So instead, we need something like one of these queries:</p>

<p>```ruby
splunk_servers = search(:node, &ldquo;recipes:splunk42\:\:server&rdquo;)</p>

<h1>or</h1>

<p>splunk_servers = search(:node, &ldquo;#{node[&lsquo;splunk&rsquo;][&lsquo;server_search_query&rsquo;]}&rdquo;)
```</p>

<p>The problem with the first is similar to the problem with the first
(<code>role:splunk-server</code>), we need knowledge about the run list in order
to search properly. The problem with the second is that we now have to
worry about constructing a query properly as a string that gets
interpolated correctly.</p>

<p>How can we improve this? I think it is more &ldquo;Chef-like&rdquo; to use an
attribute on the server&rsquo;s node object itself that informs queries the
intention that the node is in fact a Splunk server. In our
<code>chef-splunk</code> cookbook, we use <code>node['splunk']['is_server']</code>. The
query looks like this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
splunk_servers = search(:node, "splunk_is_server:true")
</code></p>

<p>This reads clearly, and the <code>is_server</code> attribute can be set in one of
15 places (for good or bad, but that&rsquo;s a different post).</p>

<h2>Repeating Resources, Composable Recipes</h2>

<p>In the past, it was deemed okay to repeat resources across recipes
when those recipes were not included on the same node. For example,
client and server recipes that have similar resource requirements, but
may pass in separate data. Another example is in the
<a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/haproxy">haproxy</a>) cookbook I
wrote where one recipe statically manages the configuration files, and
the other uses a Chef search to populate the configuration.</p>

<p>As I have mentioned above, a lot of code was duplicated between the
client and server recipes for our <code>splunk42</code> cookbook: user and group,
the case statements, package resources, execute statements (that
haven&rsquo;t been shared here), and the service resource. It is definitely
important to ensure that all the resources needed to converge a recipe
are defined, particularly when using notifications. That is why
sometimes a recipe will have a <code>service</code> resource with no actions like
this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
service 'mything'
</code></p>

<p>However Chef 11will generate a warning about
<a href="http://tickets.opscode.com/browse/CHEF-3694">cloned resources</a> when
they are repeated in the same Chef run.</p>

<p>Why is this bad? Well, CHEF-3694 explains in more detail that
particular issue, of cloned resources. The other reason is that it
makes recipes harder to reuse when they have a larger scope than
absolutely necessary. How can we make this better? A solution to this
is to write small, composable recipes that contain resources that may
be optional for certain use cases. For example, we can put the service
resource in a recipe and include that:</p>

<p><code>ruby
service 'splunk' do
  supports :status =&gt; true, :restart =&gt; true
  provider Chef::Provider::Service::Init
  action :start
end
</code></p>

<p>Then when we need to make sure we have the <code>service</code> resource
available (e.g., for notifications):</p>

<p><code>ruby
template "#{splunk_dir}/etc/system/local/outputs.conf" do
  source 'outputs.conf.erb'
  mode 0644
  variables :splunk_servers =&gt; splunk_servers
  notifies :restart, 'service[splunk]'
end
include_recipe 'chef-splunk::service'
</code></p>

<p>Note that the service is included <em>after</em> the resource that notifies
it. This is a feature of the notification system, where the notified
resource can appear anywhere in the resource collection, and brings up
another excellent practice, which is to declare service resources
after other resources which affect their configuration. This prevents
a race condition where, if a bad config is deployed, the service would
attempt to start, fail, and cause the Chef run to exit before the
config file could correct the problem.</p>

<p>Making recipes composable in this way means that users can pick and
choose the ones they want. Our <code>chef-splunk</code> cookbook has a
prescriptive default recipe, but the client and server recipes mainly
include the others they need. If someone doesn&rsquo;t share our opinion on
this for their use case, they can pick and choose the ones they want.
Perhaps they have the <code>splunk</code> user and group created on systems
through some other means. They won&rsquo;t need the <code>chef-splunk::user</code>
recipe, and can write their own wrapper to handle that. Overall this
is good, though it does mean there are multiple places where a user
must look to follow a recipe.</p>

<h2>Plaintext Secrets</h2>

<p>Managing secrets is one of the hardest problems to solve in system
administration and configuration management. In Chef, it is very easy
to simply set attributes, or use data bag items for authentication
credentials. Our old <code>splunk42</code> cookbook had this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
splunk_password = node[:splunk][:auth].split(':')[1]
</code></p>

<p>Where <code>node[:splunk][:auth]</code> was set in a role with the
<code>username:password</code>. This isn&rsquo;t particularly <em>bad</em> since our Chef
server runs on a private network and is secured with HTTPS and RSA
keys, but a defense in depth security posture has more controls in
place for secrets.</p>

<p>How can this be improved? At Chef, we started using
<a href="https://github.com/Nordstrom/chef-vault">Chef Vault</a> to manage
secrets. I wrote a
<a href="http://www.getchef.com/blog/2013/09/19/managing-secrets-with-chef-vault/">post about chef-vault</a>
a few months ago, so I won&rsquo;t dig too deep into the details here. The
current <code>chef-splunk</code> cookbook loads the authentication information
like this:</p>

<p>```ruby
splunk_auth_info = chef_vault_item(:vault, &ldquo;splunk_#{node.chef_environment}&rdquo;)[&lsquo;auth&rsquo;]
user, pw = splunk_auth_info.split(&lsquo;:&rsquo;)</p>

<p>execute &ldquo;#{splunk_cmd} edit user #{user} -password &lsquo;#{pw}&rsquo; -role admin -auth admin:changeme&rdquo; do
  not_if { ::File.exists?(&ldquo;#{splunk_dir}/etc/.setup<em>#{user}</em>password&rdquo;) }
end</p>

<p>file &ldquo;#{splunk_dir}/etc/.setup<em>#{user}</em>password&rdquo; do
  content &lsquo;true\n&rsquo;
  owner &lsquo;root&rsquo;
  group &lsquo;root&rsquo;
  mode 00600
end
```</p>

<p>The first line loads the authentication information from the
encrypted-with-chef-vault data bag item. Then we make a couple of
convenient local variables, and change the password from Splunk&rsquo;s
built-in default. Then, we control convergence of the execute by
writing a file that indicates that the password has been set.</p>

<p>The advantage of this over attributes or data bag items is that the
content is encrypted. The advantage over regular encrypted data bags
is that we don&rsquo;t need to distribute the secret key out to every
system, we can update the list of nodes that have access with a knife
command.</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>Neither Chef (the company), nor I are here to tell anyone how to
write cookbooks. One of the benefits of Chef (the product) is its
flexibility, allowing users to write blocks of Ruby code in recipes
that quickly solve an immediate problem. That&rsquo;s how we got to where we
were with <code>splunk42</code>, and we certainly have other cookbooks that can
be refactored similarly. When it comes to sharing cookbooks with the
community, well-factored, easy to follow, understand, and use code is
preferred.</p>

<p>Many of the ideas here came from community members like Miah Johnson,
Noah Kantrowitz, Jamie Winsor, and Mike Fiedler. I owe them thanks for
challenging me over the years on a lot of the older patterns that I
held onto. Together we can build better automation through cookbooks,
and a strong collaborative community. I hope this information is
helpful to those goals.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Secrets With Chef Vault]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2013/09/10/managing-secrets-with-chef-vault/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T09:30:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2013/09/10/managing-secrets-with-chef-vault</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two years ago, I wrote a post about
<a href="http://jtimberman.housepub.org/blog/2011/08/06/encrypted-data-bag-for-postfix-sasl-authentication/">using Chef encrypted data bags</a>
for SASL authentication with Postfix. At the time, my ISP didn&rsquo;t allow
non-authenticated SMTP, so I had to find a solution so I could get
cronspam and other vital email from my servers at home. I&rsquo;ve since
switched ISPs to one that doesn&rsquo;t care so much about this, so I&rsquo;m not
using any of that code anymore.</p>

<p>However, that doesn&rsquo;t mean I don&rsquo;t have secrets to manage! I actually
don&rsquo;t for my personal systems due to what I&rsquo;m managing with Chef now,
but we certainly do for Opscode&rsquo;s hosted Enterprise Chef environment.
The usual suspects for any web application are required: database
passwords, SSL certificates, service API tokens, etc.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re evaluating chef-vault as a possible solution. This blog post
will serve as notes for me so I can remember what I did when my
terminal history is gone, and hopefully information for you to be able
to use in your own environment.</p>

<h1>Chef Vault</h1>

<p>Chef Vault is an
<a href="https://github.com/Nordstrom/chef-vault">open source project</a>
published by <a href="http://nordstrom.com">Nordstrom</a>. It is distributed as a
RubyGem. You&rsquo;ll need it installed on your local workstation so you can
encrypt sensitive secrets, and on any systems that need to decrypt
said secrets. Since the workstation is where we&rsquo;re going to start,
install the gem. I&rsquo;ll talk about using this in a recipe later.</p>

<p><code>
% gem install chef-vault
</code></p>

<h1>Use Cases</h1>

<p>Now, for the use cases, I&rsquo;m going to take two fairly simple examples,
and explain how chef-vault works along the way.</p>

<ol>
<li>A username/password combination. The <code>vaultuser</code> will be created on
the system with Chef&rsquo;s built-in <code>user</code> resource.</li>
<li>A file with sensitive content. In this case, I&rsquo;m going to use a
junk RSA private key for <code>vaultuser</code>.</li>
</ol>


<p>Secrets are generally one of these things. Either a value passed into
a command-line program (like <code>useradd</code>) or a file that should live on
disk (like an SSL certificate or RSA key).</p>

<h1>Command-line Structure</h1>

<p>Chef Vault includes knife plugins to allow you to manage the secrets
from your workstation, uploading them to the Chef Server just like
normal data bags. The secrets themselves live in Data Bags on the Chef
Server. The &ldquo;bag&rdquo; is called the &ldquo;vault&rdquo; for chef-vault.</p>

<p>After installation, the <code>encrypt</code> and <code>decrypt</code> sub-commands will be
available for knife.</p>

<p><code>
knife encrypt create [VAULT] [ITEM] [VALUES] --mode MODE --search SEARCH --admins ADMINS --json FILE
knife encrypt delete [VAULT] [ITEM] --mode MODE
knife encrypt remove [VAULT] [ITEM] [VALUES] --mode MODE --search SEARCH --admins ADMINS
knife rotate secret [VAULT] [ITEM] --mode MODE
knife encrypt update [VAULT] [ITEM] [VALUES] --mode MODE --search SEARCH --admins ADMINS --json FILE
knife decrypt [VAULT] [ITEM] [VALUES] --mode MODE
</code></p>

<p>The
<a href="https://github.com/Nordstrom/chef-vault/blob/master/README.md">README</a>
and
<a href="https://github.com/Nordstrom/chef-vault/blob/master/KNIFE_EXAMPLES.md">Examples</a>
document these quite well.</p>

<h2>Mode: Solo vs Client</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m using Chef with a Chef Server (Enterprise Chef), so I&rsquo;ll specify
<code>--mode client</code> for the knife commands.</p>

<p>It is important to note the <code>MODE</code> in the chef-vault knife plugin
commands affects where the encrypted data bags will be saved. Chef
supports data bags with both Solo and Client/Server use. When using
chef-solo, you&rsquo;ll need to configure <code>data_bag_path</code> in your
<code>knife.rb</code>. That is, even if you&rsquo;re using Solo, since these are knife
plugins, the configuration is for knife, not chef-solo. I&rsquo;m using a
Chef Server though, so I&rsquo;m going to use <code>--mode client</code>.</p>

<h1>Create a User with a Password</h1>

<p>The user I&rsquo;m going to create is the arbitrarily named <code>vaultuser</code>,
with the super secret password, <code>chef-vault</code>. I&rsquo;m going to use this on
a Linux system with SHA512 hashing, so first I generate a password
using mkpasswd:</p>

<p><code>
% mkpasswd -m sha-512
Password: chef-vault
$6$VqEIDjsp$7NtPMhA9cnxvSMTE9l7DMmydJJEymi9b4t1Vhk475vrWlfxMgVb3bDLhpk/RZt0J3X7l5H8WnqFgvq3dIa9Kt/
</code></p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: This is the <code>mkpasswd(1)</code> command from the Ubuntu 10.04
  <a href="http://packages.ubuntu.com/lucid/mkpasswd">mkpasswd package</a>.</p>

<h2>Create the Item</h2>

<p>The command I&rsquo;m going to use is <code>knife encrypt create</code> since this is a
new secret. I&rsquo;ll show two examples. First, I&rsquo;ll pass in the raw JSON
data as &ldquo;values&rdquo;. You would do this if you&rsquo;re not going to store the
unencrypted secret on disk or in a repository. Second, I&rsquo;ll pass a
JSON file. You would do this if you want to store the unencrypted
secret on disk or in a repository.</p>

<p><code>
% knife encrypt create secrets vaultuser \
  '{"vaultuser":"$6$VqEIDjsp$7NtPMhA9cnxvSMTE9l7DMmydJJEymi9b4t1Vhk475vrWlfxMgVb3bDLhpk/RZt0J3X7l5H8WnqFgvq3dIa9Kt/"}' \
  --search 'role:base' \
  --admins jtimberman --mode client
</code></p>

<p>The <code>[VALUES]</code> in this command is raw JSON that will be created in the
data bag item by <code>chef-vault</code>. The <code>--search</code> option tells chef-vault
to use the <strong>public</strong> keys of the nodes matching the SOLR query for
encrypting the value. Then during the Chef run, chef-vault uses those
node&rsquo;s <strong>private</strong> keys to decrypt the value. The <code>--admins</code> option tells chef-vault
the list of users on the Chef Server who are also allowed to decrypt
the secret. This is specified as a comma separated string for
multiple admins. Finally, as I mentioned, I&rsquo;m using a Chef Server so I
need to specify <code>--mode client</code>, since &ldquo;solo&rdquo; is the default.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the equivalent, using a JSON file named <code>secrets_vaultuser.json</code>. It has the content:</p>

<p><code>json
{"vaultuser":"$6$VqEIDjsp$7NtPMhA9cnxvSMTE9l7DMmydJJEymi9b4t1Vhk475vrWlfxMgVb3bDLhpk/RZt0J3X7l5H8WnqFgvq3dIa9Kt/"}
</code></p>

<p>The command is:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt create secrets vaultuser \
  --json secrets_vaultuser.json
  --search 'role:base' \
  --admins jtimberman --mode client
</code></p>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s see what has been created on the Chef Server. I&rsquo;ll use the
core Chef knife plugin, <code>data bag item show</code> for this.</p>

<p><code>text
% knife data bag show secrets
vaultuser
vaultuser_keys
</code></p>

<p>I now have a &ldquo;secrets&rdquo; data bag, with two items. The first,
<code>vaultuser</code> is the one that contains the actual secret. Let&rsquo;s see:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife data bag show secrets vaultuser
id:        vaultuser
vaultuser:
  cipher:         aes-256-cbc
  encrypted_data: j+/fFM7ist6I7K360GNfzSgu6ix63HGyXN2ZAd99R6H4TAJ4pQKuFNpJXYnC
  SXA5n68xn9frxHAJNcLuDXCkEv+F/MnW9vMlTaiuwW/jO++vS5mIxWU170mR
  EgeB7gvPH7lfUdJFURNGQzdiTSSFua9E06kAu9dcrT83PpoQQzk=
  iv:             cu2Ugw+RpTDVRu1QaaAfug==
  version:        1
</code></p>

<p>As you can see, I have encrypted data. I also told chef-vault that my
user can decrypt this. I need to use the knife plugin to do so:</p>

<p>```text
% knife decrypt secrets vaultuser &lsquo;vaultuser&rsquo; &mdash;mode client
secrets/vaultuser</p>

<pre><code>vaultuser: $6$VqEIDjsp$7NtPMhA9cnxvSMTE9l7DMmydJJEymi9b4t1Vhk475vrWlfxMgVb3bDLhpk/RZt0J3X7l5H8WnqFgvq3dIa9Kt/
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The <code>'vaultuser'</code> in quotes is the key from the hash of JSON data that
I specified earlier. As you can see, the password is that which was
generated from the mkpasswd command earlier.</p>

<p>But what nodes have access to decrypt this password? That&rsquo;s what
chef-vault stored in the <code>vaultuser_keys</code> item. Let&rsquo;s look:</p>

<p>```text
% knife data bag show secrets vaultuser_keys
admins:              jtimberman
clients:
  os-945926465950316
  os-2790002246935003
id:                  vaultuser_keys
jtimberman:          0Q2bhw/kJl2aIVEwqY6wYhrrfdz9fdsf8tCiIrBih2ZORvV7EEIpzzKQggRX
4P4vnVQjMjfkRwIXndTzctCJONQYF50OSZi5ByXWqbich9iCWvVIbnhcLWSp
z5mQoSTNXyZz/JQZGnubkckh4wGLBFDrLJ6WKl6UNXH1dRwqDNo5sEK7/3Wn
b4ztVSRxzB01wVli0wLvFSZzGsKYJYINBcidnbIgLh/xGYGtBJVlgG2z/7TV
uN0b/qvGj8VlhbS6zPlwh39O3mexDdkLwry/+gbO1nj8qKNkKDKaix5zypwE
XdmdfMKNYGaM6kzG8cwuKZXLAgGAgblVUB1HP8+8kQ==</p>

<p>os-2790002246935003: kGQLsxsFmBe9uPuWxZpKiNBnqJq55hQZJLgaKdjG2Vvivv98RrFGz1y8Xbwe
uzeSgPgAURCZmxpNxpHrwvvKcvL77sBOL6TTKiNzs8n5B3ZOawy17dsuG24v
41R0cRMnYLgbLcjln9dpVe4Esr4goPxko+1XqBPik1SBapthQq/pLUJ1BIKh
Fxu1QVGj1w4HPUftLaUzeS33jKbtfvgZyZsYZBdVCVEVidOxC90WRf4wtkd6
Ueyj+0gd1QKv84Q387O1R5LtRMS6u+17PJinrcRIkVNZ6P1z6oT2Dasfvrex
rK3s5vD7v6jpkUW12Wj74Lz3Z6x3sKuIDzCtvEUnWw==</p>

<p>os-945926465950316:  XzTJrJ3TZZZ1u9L9p6DZledf3bo2ToH2yrLGZQKPV6/ANzElHXGcYrEdtP0q
14Nz1NzsqEftzviAebUUnc6ke91ltD8s6hNQQrPJRqkUoDlM7lNEwiUiz/dD
+sFI6CSzQptO3zPrUbAlUI1Zog5h7k/CCtiYtmFRD6wbAWnxmCqvLhO1jwqL
VNJ1vfjlFsG77BDm2HFw7jgleuxRGYEgBfCCuBuW70FAdUTvNHIAwKQVkfU/
Am75UYm7N4N0E+W76ZwojLoYtXXTV/iOGG1cw3C75SVAmCsBOuxUK/otub67
zsNDsKToKa+laxzXGylrmkTricYXIqVpIQO8OL5nnw==
```</p>

<p>As we can see, I have two nodes that are API clients with access to
decrypt the data bag items. These values are all generated by
chef-vault, and I&rsquo;ll talk about how to update the list and rotate
secrets later in this post.</p>

<h2>Manage a User Password</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s manage a user resource with a password set to the value from our
encrypted data bag using Chef Vault.</p>

<p>First, I created a cookbook named <code>vault</code>, and added it to the base
role. It contains the following recipe:</p>

<p>```ruby
chef_gem &ldquo;chef-vault&rdquo;
require &ldquo;chef-vault&rdquo;</p>

<p>vault = ChefVault::Item.load(&ldquo;secrets&rdquo;, &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;)</p>

<p>user &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo; do
  password vault[&lsquo;vaultuser&rsquo;]
  home &ldquo;/home/vaultuser&rdquo;
  supports :manage_home => true
  shell &ldquo;/bin/bash&rdquo;
  comment &ldquo;Chef Vault User&rdquo;
end
```</p>

<p>Let me break this down.</p>

<p><code>ruby
chef_gem "chef-vault"
require "chef-vault"
</code></p>

<p><code>chef-vault</code> is distributed as a RubyGem, and I want to use it in my
recipe(s), so here I use the
<a href="http://docs.opscode.com/resource_chef_gem.html"><code>chef_gem</code> resource</a>.
Then, I require it like any other Ruby library.</p>

<p><code>ruby
vault = ChefVault::Item.load("secrets", "vaultuser")
</code></p>

<p>This is where the decryption happens. If I do this under a
<code>chef-shell</code>, I can see:</p>

<p><code>text
chef:recipe &gt; vault = ChefVault::Item.load("secrets", "vaultuser")
 =&gt; data_bag_item["secrets", "vaultuser", {"id"=&gt;"vaultuser", "vaultuser"=&gt;"$6$VqEIDjsp$7NtPMhA9cnxvSMTE9l7DMmydJJEymi9b4t1Vhk475vrWlfxMgVb3bDLhpk/RZt0J3X7l5H8WnqFgvq3dIa9Kt/"}]
</code></p>

<p><code>ChefVault::Item.load</code> takes two arguments, the &ldquo;vault&rdquo; or data bag,
in this case <code>secrets</code>, and the &ldquo;item&rdquo;, in this case <code>vaultuser</code>. It
returns a data bag item. Then in the
<a href="http://docs.opscode.com/resource_user.html"><code>user</code> resource</a>, I use
the password:</p>

<p><code>ruby
user "vaultuser" do
  password vault['vaultuser']
  home "/home/vaultuser"
  supports :manage_home =&gt; true
  shell "/bin/bash"
  comment "Chef Vault User"
end
</code></p>

<p>The important resource attribute here is <code>password</code>, where I&rsquo;m using
the local variable, <code>vault</code> and the <code>vaultuser</code> key from the item as
decrypted by <code>ChefVault::Item.load</code>. When Chef runs, it will look like
this:</p>

<p>```text
Recipe: vault::default
  * chef_gem[chef-vault] action install</p>

<pre><code>- install version 2.0.1 of package chef-vault
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>chef_gem[chef-vault] action install (up to date)</li>
<li>user[vaultuser] action create

<ul>
<li>create user user[vaultuser]
```</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, I can su to <code>vaultuser</code> using the password I created:</p>

<p><code>text
ubuntu@-2790002246935003:~$ su - vaultuser
Password: chef-vault
vaultuser@os-2790002246935003:~$ id
uid=1001(vaultuser) gid=1001(vaultuser) groups=1001(vaultuser)
vaultuser@os-2790002246935003:~$ pwd
/home/vaultuser
</code></p>

<p>Yay! To show that the user was created with the right password,
here&rsquo;s the DEBUG log output:</p>

<p><code>text
INFO: Processing user[vaultuser] action create ((irb#1) line 12)
DEBUG: user[vaultuser] user does not exist
DEBUG: user[vaultuser] setting comment to Chef Vault User
DEBUG: user[vaultuser] setting password to $6$VqEIDjsp$7NtPMhA9cnxvSMTE9l7DMmydJJEymi9b4t1Vhk475vrWlfxMgVb3bDLhpk/RZt0J3X7l5H8WnqFgvq3dIa9Kt/
DEBUG: user[vaultuser] setting shell to /bin/bash
INFO: user[vaultuser] created
</code></p>

<p>Next, I&rsquo;ll create a secret that is a file rendered on the system.</p>

<h1>Create a Private SSH Key</h1>

<p>Suppose this <code>vaultuser</code> is to be used for deploying code by cloning a
repository. It will need a private SSH key to authenticate, so I&rsquo;ll
create one, with an empty passphrase in this case.</p>

<p><code>text
% ssh-keygen -b 4096 -t rsa -f vaultuser-ssh
Generating public/private rsa key pair.
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved in vaultuser-ssh.
Your public key has been saved in vaultuser-ssh.pub.
</code></p>

<p>Get the SHA256 checksum of the private key. I use SHA256 because
that&rsquo;s what Chef uses for file content. We&rsquo;ll use this to verify
content later.</p>

<p><code>text
% sha256sum vaultuser-ssh
a83221c243c9d39d20761e87db6c781ed0729b8ff4c3b330214ebca26e2ea89d  vaultuser-ssh
</code></p>

<p>Assume that I also
<a href="https://help.github.com/articles/generating-ssh-keys">created the SSH key on GitHub</a>
for this user.</p>

<p>In order to have a file&rsquo;s contents be a JSON value for the data bag
item, I&rsquo;ll remove the newlines (<code>\n</code>), and generate the JSON:</p>

<p>```text
ruby -rjson -e &lsquo;puts JSON.generate({&ldquo;vaultuser-ssh-private&rdquo; => File.read(&ldquo;vaultuser-ssh&rdquo;)})&rsquo; \</p>

<blockquote><p>secrets_vaultuser-ssh-private.json
```</p></blockquote>

<p>Now, create the secret on the Chef Server:</p>

<p><code>text
knife encrypt create secrets vaultuser-ssh-private \
  --search 'role:base' \
  --json secrets_vaultuser-ssh-private.json \
  --admins jtimberman \
  --mode client
</code></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s verify the server has what we need:</p>

<p>```text
% knife data bag show secrets vaultuser-ssh-private
id:                    vaultuser-ssh-private
vaultuser-ssh-private:
  cipher:         aes-256-cbc
  encrypted_data: mRRToM2N/0F+OyJxkYlHo/cUtHSIuy69ROAKuGoHIhX9Fr5vFTCM4RyWQSTN
  trimmed for brevity even though scrollbars
% knife decrypt secrets vaultuser-ssh-private &lsquo;vaultuser-ssh-private&rsquo; &mdash;mode client
secrets/vaultuser-ssh-private</p>

<pre><code>vaultuser-ssh-private: -----BEGIN RSA PRIVATE KEY-----
</code></pre>

<p>trimmed for brevity even though scrollbars
```</p>

<h2>Manage the Key File</h2>

<p>Now, I&rsquo;ll manage the private key file with the vault cookbook.</p>

<p>```ruby
vault_ssh = ChefVault::Item.load(&ldquo;secrets&rdquo;, &ldquo;vaultuser-ssh-private&rdquo;)</p>

<p>directory &ldquo;/home/vaultuser/.ssh&rdquo; do
  owner &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;
  group &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;
  mode 0700
end</p>

<p>file &ldquo;/home/vaultuser/.ssh/id_rsa&rdquo; do
  content vault_ssh[&ldquo;vaultuser-ssh-private&rdquo;]
  owner &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;
  group &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;
  mode 0600
end
```</p>

<p>Again, let&rsquo;s break this up a bit. First, load the item from the
encrypted data bag like we did before.</p>

<p><code>ruby
vault_ssh = ChefVault::Item.load("secrets", "vaultuser-ssh-private")
</code></p>

<p>Next, make sure that the vaultuser has an <code>.ssh</code> directory with the
correct permissions.</p>

<p><code>ruby
directory "/home/vaultuser/.ssh" do
  owner "vaultuser"
  group "vaultuser"
  mode 0700
end
</code></p>

<p>Finally, manage the content of the private key file with a <code>file</code>
resource and the <code>content</code> resource attribute. The value of
<code>vault_ssh["vaultuser-ssh-private"]</code> will be a string, with <code>\n</code>&rsquo;s
embedded, but when it&rsquo;s rendered on disk, it will display properly.</p>

<p><code>ruby
file "/home/vaultuser/.ssh/id_rsa" do
  content vault_ssh["vaultuser-ssh-private"]
  owner "vaultuser"
  group "vaultuser"
  mode 0600
end
</code></p>

<p>And now run chef on a target node:</p>

<p>```text
Recipe: vault::default
  * chef_gem[chef-vault] action install (up to date)
  * user[vaultuser] action create (up to date)
  * directory[/home/vaultuser/.ssh] action create</p>

<pre><code>- create new directory /home/vaultuser/.ssh
- change mode from '' to '0700'
- change owner from '' to 'vaultuser'
- change group from '' to 'vaultuser'
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>file[/home/vaultuser/.ssh/id_rsa] action create

<ul>
<li>create new file /home/vaultuser/.ssh/id_rsa with content checksum a83221
  &mdash;&ndash; /tmp/chef-tempfile20130909-1918-1v5hezo 2013-09-09 22:41:21.887239999 +0000
  +++ /tmp/chef-diff20130909-1918-xwbmsn  2013-09-09 22:41:21.883240065 +0000
  @@ -0,0 +1,51 @@
  +&mdash;&mdash;-BEGIN RSA PRIVATE KEY&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
  +MIIJJwIBAAKCAgEAtZmwFTlVOBbr2ZfG+cDtUGx04xCcgaa0p0ISmeyMEoGYH/CP
  output trimmed because its long even though scrollbars again
```</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Note the content checksum, <code>a83221</code>. This will match the checksum of
the source file from earlier (scroll up!), and the one rendered:</p>

<p><code>text
ubuntu@os-2790002246935003:~$ sudo sha256sum /home/vaultuser/.ssh/id_rsa
a83221c243c9d39d20761e87db6c781ed0729b8ff4c3b330214ebca26e2ea89d  /home/vaultuser/.ssh/id_rsa
</code></p>

<p>Yay! Now, we can SSH to GitHub (note, this is fake GitHub for example
purposes).</p>

<p><code>text
ubuntu@os-2790002246935003:~$ su - vaultuser
Password: chef-vault
vaultuser@os-2790002246935003:~$ ssh -i .ssh/id_rsa github@172.31.7.15
$ hostname
os-945926465950316
$ id
uid=1002(github) gid=1002(github) groups=1002(github)
</code></p>

<h1>Updating a Secret</h1>

<p>What happens if we need to update a secret? For example, if an
administrator leaves the organization, we will want to change the
<code>vaultuser</code> password (and SSH private key).</p>

<p><code>text
% mkpasswd -m sha-512
Password: gone-user
$6$zM5STNtXdmsrOSm$svJr0tauijqqxTjnMIGJGJPv5V3ovMFCQo.ZDBleiL.yOxcngRqh9yAjpMAsMBA7RlKPv5DKFd1aPZm/wUoKs.
</code></p>

<p>The <code>encrypt create</code> command will return an error if the target
already exists:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt create secrets vaultuser --search 'role:base' --json secrets_vaultuser.json --admins jtimberman --mode client
ERROR: ChefVault::Exceptions::ItemAlreadyExists: secrets/vaultuser already exists, use 'knife encrypt remove' and 'knife encrypt update' to make changes.
</code></p>

<p>So, I need to use <code>encrypt update</code>. <strong>Note</strong> make sure that the
contents of the JSON file are valid JSON.</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt update secrets vaultuser --search 'role:base' --json secrets_vaultuser.json --admins jtimberman --mode client
</code></p>

<p><code>encrypt update</code> only updates the things that change, so I can also
shorten this:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt update secrets vaultuser --json secrets_vaultuser.json --mode client
</code></p>

<p>Since the search and the admins didn&rsquo;t change.</p>

<p>Verify it:</p>

<p>```text
% knife decrypt secrets vaultuser &lsquo;vaultuser&rsquo; &mdash;mode client
secrets/vaultuser</p>

<pre><code>vaultuser: $6$zM5STNtXdmsrOSm$svJr0tauijqqxTjnMIGJGJPv5V3ovMFCQo.ZDBleiL.yOxcngRqh9yAjpMAsMBA7RlKPv5DKFd1aPZm/wUoKs.
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Now, just run Chef on any nodes affected.</p>

<p>```text
Recipe: vault::default
  * chef_gem[chef-vault] action install (up to date)
  * user[vaultuser] action create</p>

<pre><code>- alter user user[vaultuser]
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>directory[/home/vaultuser/.ssh] action create (up to date)</li>
<li>file[/home/vaultuser/.ssh/id_rsa] action create (up to date)
Chef Client finished, 1 resources updated
```</li>
</ul>


<p>And su to the vault user with the <code>gone-user</code> password:</p>

<p><code>text
ubuntu@os-2790002246935003:~$ su - vaultuser
Password: gone-user
vaultuser@os-2790002246935003:~$
</code></p>

<h1>Managing Access to Items</h1>

<p>There are three common scenarios which require managing the access to an item
in the vault.</p>

<ol>
<li>A system needs to be taken offline, or otherwise prevented from
accessing the item(s).</li>
<li>A new system comes online that needs access.</li>
<li>An admin user has left the organization.</li>
<li>A new admin user has joined the organization.</li>
</ol>


<p>Suppose we have a system that we need to take offline for some reason,
so we want to disable its access to a secret. Or, perhaps we have a
user who has left the organization that was an admin. We can do that in a
few ways.</p>

<h2>Update the Vault Item</h2>

<p>The most straightforward way to manage access to an item is to use the
<code>update</code> or <code>remove</code> sub-commands.</p>

<h3>Remove a System</h3>

<p>Suppose I want to remove node <code>DEADNODE</code>, I can qualify the search to
exclude the node named <code>DEADNODE</code>:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt update secrets vaultuser \
  --search 'role:base NOT name:DEADNODE' \
  --json secrets_vaultuser.json \
  --admins jtimberman --mode client
</code></p>

<p>Note, as before, admins didn&rsquo;t change so I don&rsquo;t need to pass that
argument.</p>

<h3>Add a New System</h3>

<p>If the node has run Chef and is indexed on the Chef Server already,
simply rerun the update command with the search:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt update secrets vaultuser \
  --search 'role:base' \
  --json secrets_vaultuser.json \
  --admins jtimberman --mode client
</code></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a bit of a &ldquo;Chicken and Egg&rdquo; problem here, in that a new node
might not be indexed for search if it tried to load the secret during
a bootstrap beforehand. For example, if I create an OpenStack instance
with the base role in its run list, the node doesn&rsquo;t exist for the
search yet. A solution here is to create the node with an empty run
list, allowing it to register with the Chef Server, and then use
<code>knife bootstrap</code> to rerun Chef with the proper run list. This is
annoying, but no one claimed that chef-vault would solve <em>all</em>
problems with shared secret management :&ndash;).</p>

<h3>Remove an Admin</h3>

<p>The admins argument takes a list. Earlier, I only had my userid as an
admin. Suppose I created the item with &ldquo;bofh&rdquo; as an admin too:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt create secrets vaultuser \
  --search 'role:base' \
  --json secrets_vaultuser.json \
  --admins "jtimberman,bofh" --mode client
</code></p>

<p>To remove the bofh user, use the <code>encrypt remove</code> subcommand. In this
case, the <code>--admins</code> argument is the list of admins to remove, rather
than add.</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt remove secrets vaultuser --admins bofh --mode client
</code></p>

<h3>Add a New Admin</h3>

<p>I want to add &ldquo;mandi&rdquo; as an administrator because she&rsquo;s awesome and
will help manage our secrets. As above, I just pass a comma-separated
string, <code>"jtimberman,mandi"</code> to the <code>--admins</code> argument.</p>

<p><code>text
% knife encrypt update secrets vaultuser \
  --search 'role:base' \
  --json secrets_vaultuser.json \
  --admins "jtimberman,mandi" --mode client
</code></p>

<h2>Regenerate the Client</h2>

<p>The heavyhanded way to remove access is to regenerate the API client
on the Chef Server. For example, of my nodes, say I want to remove
<code>os-945926465950316</code>:</p>

<p><code>text
% knife client reregister os-945926465950316
-----BEGIN RSA PRIVATE KEY-----
MIIEpAIBAAKCAQEAybzwv53tDLIzW+GHRJwLthZmiGTfZVyqQX6m6RGuZjemEIdy
trim trim
</code></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re familiar with Chef Server&rsquo;s authentication cycle, you&rsquo;ll
know that until that private key is copied to the node, it will
completely fail to authenticate. However, once the
<code>/etc/chef/client.pem</code> file is updated with the content from the knife
command, we&rsquo;ll see that the node fails to read the Chef Vault item:</p>

<h1>```text</h1>

<h1>Recipe Compile Error in /var/chef/cache/cookbooks/vault/recipes/default.rb</h1>

<h2>OpenSSL::PKey::RSAError</h2>

<p>padding check failed</p>

<h2>Cookbook Trace:</h2>

<p>  /var/chef/cache/cookbooks/vault/recipes/default.rb:4:in `from_file'</p>

<h2>Relevant File Content:</h2>

<p>/var/chef/cache/cookbooks/vault/recipes/default.rb:</p>

<p>  1:  chef_gem &ldquo;chef-vault&rdquo;
  2:  require &ldquo;chef-vault&rdquo;
  3:
  4>> vault = ChefVault::Item.load(&ldquo;secrets&rdquo;, &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;)
  5:
  6:  user &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo; do
  7:    password vault[&ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;]
  8:    home &ldquo;/home/vaultuser&rdquo;
  9:    supports :manage_home => true
 10:    shell &ldquo;/bin/bash&rdquo;
 11:    comment &ldquo;Chef Vault User&rdquo;
 12:  end
 13:
```</p>

<p><strong>Note</strong> I say this is heavy-handed because if you make a mistake, you
  need to re-upload every single secret that this node needs access to.</p>

<h2>Removing Users</h2>

<p>We can also remove user access from Enterprise Chef simply by
disassociating that user from the organization on the Chef Server. I
won&rsquo;t show an example of that here, since I&rsquo;m using Opscode&rsquo;s hosted
Enterprise Chef server and I&rsquo;m the only admin, however :&ndash;).</p>

<h1>Backing Up Secrets</h1>

<p>To back up the secrets, as encrypted data from the Chef Server, use
<code>knife-essentials</code> (comes with Chef 11+, available as a RubyGem for
Chef 10).</p>

<p><code>text
% knife download data_bags/secrets/
Created data_bags/secrets/vaultuser_keys.json
Created data_bags/secrets/vaultuser.json
Created data_bags/secrets/vaultuser-ssh-private_keys.json
Created data_bags/secrets/vaultuser-ssh-private.json
</code></p>

<p>For example, the vaultuser.json file looks like this:</p>

<p>```json
{
  &ldquo;id&rdquo;: &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;,
  &ldquo;vaultuser&rdquo;: {</p>

<pre><code>"encrypted_data": "3yREwInxdyKpf8nuTIivXAeuEzHt7o4vF4FsOwmVLHmMWol5nCBoMWF0YdaW\n3P3NpEAAAxYEYeJYdVkrdLqjjB2kTJdx0+ceh/RBHBWqmSeHOWFH9pCRGjV8\nfS5XaTueShb320b/+Ia8iqUJJWg6utnbJCDx+VMcGNggPXgPKC8=\n",
"iv": "EI+y74Uj2uwq7EVaP+0K6Q==\n",
"version": 1,
"cipher": "aes-256-cbc"
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>Since these are encrypted using a strong cipher (AES 256), they should
be safe to store in repository. Unless you think the NSA has access to
that repository ;&ndash;).</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>Secrets management is hard! Especially when you need to store secrets
that are used by multiple systems, services, and people. Chef&rsquo;s
encrypted data bag feature isn&rsquo;t a panacea, but it certainly helps.
Hopefully, this blog post was informative. While I don&rsquo;t always
respond, I do read all comments posted here via Disqus, so let me know
if something is out of whack, or needs an update.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
